[Music]
this program is brought to you by
Stanford University please visit us at
stanford.edu
okay so we were about to embark on a
distant journey into a journey into a um
large black
hole before we do let me remind you of
one or
two facts I just hope we have enough oh
I actually brought some
pens anyway let me just go back for a
moment to The Accelerated reference
frame and just remind
you of what the various facts about it
are excuse me the accelerated reference
frame
was was a frame in which every
Observer is moving on a hyperbolic
trajectory as you get closer and closer
to the light cone here the
trajectory has an increased acceleration
and you can see that from the fact that
it has to turn the corner in a short in
a smaller amount of uh
space so it's not like an accelerated
coordinate system in the tonian
mechanics where everybody part takes of
the same exact acceleration and all move
off
simultaneously but rather the the
acceleration gets larger and
larger As you move
toward last is this an example why
special relativity does not apply to
accelerated this is an accelerated
reference but
met but that's also true in the that's
also true in the vicinity of black
hole that this this point or this whole
line in fact is replaces the black hole
Horizon and if you're standing if you're
supported 10 m or 100 meters away from
the black hole Horizon you have one
acceleration well let's first take the
Earth if you lower down to the surface
of the Earth well from a large distance
uh and not lowered down but you
supported of course your acceleration is
larger the closer you are to the Center
of the Earth so it's not that
surprising uh in that sense
The Accelerated reference frame is not a
very precise version of a gravitational
field because gravitational field varies
here in special relativity we already
have this property that the closest
thing to a uniformly accelerated
reference frame already has this fact
that the gravitational strength or the
acceleration that you feel varies from
this distance from this point over
here okay we also
discussed
um these are the different observers
they could be
characterized by a coordinate
R which at least along here just
represents how far they are from the
origin of coordinates over here
characterized by an r and they're also
characterized by a hyperbolic angle the
hyperbolic angle did I call it Omega
last time what did I call it
Omega such that if you want the precise
relationship with the original
coordinates on the Blackboard call them
x and
[Music]
t then to be to make the relationship
precise X is equal to R times the
hyperbolic
cosine
cosine of the hyperbolic angle
Omega and
T is equal to R * the hyperbolic s of
Omega very very much like polar
coordinates in
which X and
Y completely different uh system now but
just to just by analogy I don't use x
and t just X and Y we would write that a
point uh is given
by an r and not an Omega but a
Theta I use Omega for hyperbolic angle
but it's a kind of angle um it doesn't
go from 0 to 2 pi sorry from yeah it
doesn't go from 0 to 2 pi it goes from
minus infinity to
infinity and it's a Tim like variable
it's obviously moving more in a Time
Direction than it is in a space
Direction and it's some sort of time
along these
trajectories but uh the analog here
would just be x = r cosine Theta
ordinary cosine not
hyperbolic and y = r s of
theta okay that's just to keep in mind
the
analogy and if we work out well first
let's write the um the metric in polar
coordinates the ordinary metric the x²
Plus y^ 2 just
becomes Dr R
2 plus r 2 D Theta
squar there might be other directions
sticking out of the Blackboard we would
add them in I'll do that over
here likewise the metric over here or
Sim in similar Spirit the metric over
here just
becomes Dr r
s well let's be careful signs signs are
important d r 2 with a minus sign this
is proper
time D t^ squ and we have R 2 D Omega
squar which is the analog of the r s d
Theta squ term here Omega is like like
time so it comes in with a plus sign
here R is like space so it comes in with
a minus sign this is equal to DT
^2 minus
dx2 now if they happen to be and of
course there are additional coordinates
the additional coordinates can be
thought of as coming out of the
Blackboard what would those additional
coordinates be let's call them just Y
and Z then we would also write minus d
y^ 2 minus dz^2 and we do the same thing
here
so it's mainly R and Omega which are the
new things and they're kind of
hyperbolic polar
coordinates lines of constant
Omega which mean lines of constant time
in the accelerated coordinate system
look like
this this is Omega equals z for example
we also can have negative Omega
Omega = 1 Omega = 2 Omega = 3 Omega = 4
dot dot dot
dot
and Omega equals infinity the end of
time from the point of view of the
accelerated reference frame is just this
light cone here which is x =
t xal t of course means xal CT if I
would put put back the speeds of light
and so this is just a motion of a light
rate okay that was the that was the
hyperbolic polar coordinates we also
pointed out that anybody who finds
himself back here cannot send a message
out to uh to The Observers who are out
here of course an observer out here can
jump in can just let go of whatever the
accelerating mechanism is is let go and
fall into here in which case he can make
contact but if he stays outside which
means if he stays on these hyperbolic
trajectories but in particular stays
does not cross this line
then
uh let's give them names this is Alice
over
here Alice Who
falls through the
Horizon and Bob
well
Bob over here who continues to
accelerate after a
point Bob cannot see Alice anymore no
that's not quite
true Bob looks back let ask what Bob
sees what does c mean c means to look
with uh with
light Bob can see everything backward
along his own trajectory can see
everything back W along lightlike
directions and it takes an infinite
amount of Bob's time Omega goes to
Infinity before he's in a position to
actually see Alice right at that light
cone there so from Bob's perspective he
sees Alice
asymptotically
approaching this line we might as well
call it the Horizon it would be improper
to call it a black hole Horizon Horizon
there's no black hole here sometimes
it's called an acceleration
horizon or a rler
horizon so Bob sees Alice asymptotically
approach The rindler
Horizon relative to
Bob Alice is moving faster and faster
particularly as Bob it's Bob who's doing
the moving from our point of view but
Bob is moving mov outward with an
enormous
velocity that means that he sees
Alice moving with a large velocity what
happens when you have somebody with a
large velocity they get lorence
contracted so Bob will see Alice
Getting Thinner and thinner in the
vertical Direction not the horizontal D
Direction and as she gets sort of
squeezed onto the Horizon but Alice
doesn't see anything out of the ordinary
she just goes right through all right so
that was a setup which was intended yeah
so will Bob see Alice's time seems to
slow
down
well will Bob see Al yes yes Bob will
see Alice's time slow
down what will Alice
see yeah she just looks back and she
sees somebody scooting along an
accelerated
trajectory the okay keep in mind there's
some asymmetry here when you talk about
what Bob sees and what Alice sees let's
draw the diagram again there's some
asymmetry the question is where the
asymmetry comes from but uh let's let's
see what the asymmetry is okay so
here here's
Bob here's Alice and for Bob to see
Alice he has to look backward along
lightlike directions like that he looks
backward we all look backward I mean
when backward in
time uh we can never see anything at the
same moment that we're looking we see
things in the past he looks back and he
sees Alice at that point a little bit
later he sees Alice at that point a
little bit later he sees Alice at that
point and so
forth
Alice looks at Bob she doesn't look in
this direction she looks back this
way and she never sees Bob disappear in
fact she just sees Bob accelerating away
from
her this means she does see Bob's
motions slow
down because Bob is moving away from her
but uh something moves away from you
they seem to slow down but Alice in this
picture
never sees Bob disappear or anything
else she just keeps watching him as he
recedes further and further into the
distance along the accelerated traj
young I have a little confusion I I see
that there inter space is a is a
transform of yeah it's just coordinate
coordinate transform it is a coordinate
transform but now we imagine acceler I
don't see the the fact I don't see the
uniform acceleration no no we're
imagining now a collection of observers
this is not just a coordinate
transformation it is a coordinate
transformation but now we're imagining
observing obers who are moving at a
fixed
R so imagining a collection of observers
each one of which is at a fixed r that
means they're accelerating off and we're
asking what they see okay so that's yeah
it is a coordinate transformation but at
the same time we're imagining that there
are people located at fixed values of
the spatial coordinate R and F R means
uniform acceleration fix R means uniform
acceleration
the D Omega
s is not quite proper time no it's not
proper time it's
s sorry
again D Omega squar is not let let's say
R equals fixed R fixed R right fixed R
DS what do I write here
D to along one of these trajectories
along one of these trajectories the r is
zero the X and d y is zero so along one
of the trajectories D to is just equal
to r d Omega R is fixed and R is fixed
but the rate of proper time relative to
the rate of
Omega differs from R to R from one R to
another okay so if you had exactly the
same kind kind of clock over here as
over here as over here as over here
namely clocks which tick off proper time
they would not be ticking off Omega if
you want clocks which tick off Omega
then those clocks have to have uh
different
rates uh of reading off proper time okay
but that's that's just a question of
coordinates uh you can imagine clocks
which are built to take off Omega you'd
have to have them built different at
each point here but so let it
be for example the proper time between
here and here is longer than the proper
time between here and
here okay so if we wanted clocks which
build which read off Omega they would
have to run at a different rate each one
run at a different rate
yeah M suppose you had an
observer um who was uh going along one
of those paths M uh one of those
trajectories only their actually their
their real X component would be
displaced and real sorry gu okay and
don't use a word real well I don't know
what
how the exort but it's not it doesn't
change as R I'm just trying to put him
in a different point in space but put
the same trajectory in other words oh
you want to put another trajectory but
this two pointless space yes but which
happens have the same shape yes rather
than same acceleration so you have yeah
okay now I have heard someone argue that
they have
different gravitational potential
because of the fact that one
has displaced r value remember the
gravitational potential is not an
invariant thing you can add a constant
to the gravitational potential it
doesn't change anything you could ask
whether they feel different force on the
bottoms of their feet they don't they
feel exactly the same force on the
bottoms of their feet if they're being
supported by so they don't see each
other moving One Direction or another no
they don't stay the same distance apart
from each other in their own frames of
reference since they since they're
parallel trajectories let's draw
them they correspond to Shifting the
origin
yes by drawing the same
curve
okay now in the original coordinates
this distance is equal to this distance
is equal to this distance is equal to
this
distance just by all we've done is
translated the the
hyperbola but in the in their own
Reckoning they don't measure distance
along here w at this point he does
measure
but here if all these observers are
maintaining constant relative distance
to in their each in their own frame of
reference sees the one ahead of him
always being the same distance away not
true here because of Laurent
contraction
right so you could call this an
accelerated coordinate system in which
you just displaced each one by the same
uh by the same amount
but it would have the property that an
observer moving along here would see the
guy in front of
him receding away and not staying the
same
distance yeah reeding or uh what's
that would the other Observer also see
the other you know isn't it just well
you got to figure it out got to figure
it out I'm not I'm not sure what each
one sees but um but whatever do they see
the distance that this person over here
sees to
him C is perhaps the wrong word the
distance that would be measured by a
measuring Rod along here would not be
the same as the distance along a
measuring Rod along here where this line
here was chosen to be the spacelike
surface for a moving Observer over here
would not be the same so
I believe they I believe he would see
him recede but I it's something we got
to figure out and uh
right
uh the properties of what each one sees
would depend on time in particular so it
wouldn't be a static description from
the point of view of the accelerated
reference
frame okay so that's uh good now let me
write down I think I did write down the
short black hole metric last time did I
not and the main thing I want to do
today is to show you the connection
between this and the Schwarz Shield
metric once you know that
connection between that picture and the
Schwarz Shield then there are many many
questions that you can answer simply by
thinking of the corresponding question
here okay so let's
uh let's write down the Schwarz
which looks entirely
different here it is the to squar
equals 1 - 2 m / R I'm setting the speed
of light as usual equal to
1 G thank you DT
^2 minus
1 / by 1 - 2 mg / r d r
2 plus r 2 not plus minus minus r
2 times the metric of a two-dimensional
unit sphere
why this is what we're using basically
is
um spherical
polar coordinates ordinary spherical
polar coordinates just wouldn't have
these MGS here would be dt^ 2 minus Dr R
2 - R 2times I think I called it last
time the Omega squar and the Omega
squar is
um D Theta squar or is it d^
squ d^ squ I guess Plus either cosine or
S depending on where you measure the
angle from uh
sin
f^ squar D Theta squar where Theta and
fi just looking around you and there a
polar angle and a
um and an azimuthal
angle that is the metric of the Schwarz
Shield black hole that's all there is to
it and analyzing this taking a part and
understanding
it uh is will teach you about as much
about black holes
as
uh well it'll teach you a lot about
black
holes okay incidentally just to remind
you this is also the metric of the
Earth's gravitational field but only out
beyond the surface of the Earth in other
words this is the solution the general
solution of the problem of a spherically
symmetric distribution of mass outside
of the place where that mass is in other
words for R larger than uh the
boundaries of the of the um chunk of
material as we take as
we take the object smaller and smaller
and smaller eventually it tends to be
this everywhere but of course there are
some problems in this metric some
singularities and there are two kinds of
singularities in this metric one of them
is a really nasty Singularity where if
you encountered it you would not be very
comfortable the other is a coordinate
artifact in other words a funniness of
coordinates okay the Horizon is the
place where 1 - 2 mg/ R becomes equal to
zero 2
mg equals R that's the
Horizon and why do I say something
singular is happening well first of all
is something happening to the dt^
2 notice that if you're sitting right at
R = 2 mg then the proper time and the
ordinary Schwartz Shield time this is
called Schwarz Shield time have an
infinite ratio of the rate at which they
run any amount of ordinary time
corresponds to zero proper
time so that's a little bit funny but it
really we've already seen it we see it
right here the to
squ at r equal 0 which is right at this
point over here this is a different R
incidentally I think we are going to run
into trouble if I continue to call this
R over here the same r as over
here uh no I'm going to call it
row
row I'm used to calling it row so I'm
going to call it Row D row
squ of course it's it's bound to happen
that we'll get into these kind of
conflicts of notation I called it R
originally because I wanted to compare
it with ordinary polar coordinates well
we always use r on the other hand um
that R we will see is not not quite the
same as this R it's related to it but
it's a little
different and this thing has been called
R also from time in Memorial so we have
to change notation we have to give away
to some other notation either on that
side or that side and I prefer to do it
over here okay now remember though that
R and row are related to each other they
may not they may may not be exactly the
same thing we'll find out but notice
over here here we have this Omega which
is the time from the point of view of
these accelerated observers notice that
a row equals
zero that any amount of D Omega
corresponds to no amount of
detau at row equals zero something like
that is going on over here at 2 mgal
R arbitrarily large amounts of DT
correspond to no proper time at
all okay
so these are funny points now there's
nothing physically important going on
here it's just that we've chosen
coordinates which have a particular
Center over here such that I it's
exactly if we went to Polar coordinates
ordinary polar coordinates it would just
be the statement that at the center any
amount of angle at all right at the
center corresponds to no
circumference
okay as you move out a little bit of
angle corresponds to a larger and larger
piece of Sur um of perimeter of distance
along the perimeter so there's this kind
of stagnation point in the coordinates
over here but it's not anything physical
going on uh so you see there are
situations where the coordinates can do
something funny where there really is
nothing going on
or at least nothing uh that the Observer
at that point would notice okay we're
going to try to find out is
this now that's first of all one thing
happens at uh 2mg equals R the
coefficient of dt^ SAR goes to
zero that's got to do with the fact that
clocks slow
down as you get closer and closer to the
Horizon we'll come back to it I think
but uh
but and that wouldn't be so bad but this
also does something bad at R = 2mg at
Ral 2mg this goes to 1 1 - 1 goes to
zero and even worse than going to zero
the coefficient of Dr s becomes
infinite H question all right so it
looks like there's something nasty n y
going on at Ral
2mg well if not from this term over here
which is doing something fairly similar
to what's going on over here the the r
squ term is blowing up in our face so
from one point of view that sounds like
there's something
nasty
there we'll see that there isn't okay
next at R equals z there's also
something funny happening r equal 0 the
coefficient of DT ^2 blows up but even
worse it blows up with a negative
sign when R is equal to zero this
becomes big 1 minus something big is
negative something big so the
coefficient of dt^ 2 blows up with a
negative sign and the coefficient of Dr
squared goes to
zero why no is that right let's see yes
I think so at Ral
0 what's in here becomes infinite and
therefore the coefficient of the r
squared gets smaller and smaller but
also with the wrong sign so something is
happening at R = 2 mg and in fact it's
interchanging the signs of dt^ 2 and Dr
s in other words Let's uh let's imagine
that R is less than 2 mg then this is
negative and this one is
positive this term has negative this one
there been
interchange of what was space like with
what was time like now does that mean
that space has become time and time has
become space no it just means that the
coordinates are doing something funny
and we'll come back to what it
is all right let me change let me take
apart this metric a little
more instead of working with
row I want to invent another
variable I don't know what to call it
I've run out of radial
variables I hate to introduce another
coordinate okay I'm going to do what I
have to I have no
choice I'm going to take row squared and
give it a new
name okay let's
see yeah give me a name for row squ
capital r capital r okay r^ 2 equal
capital
r then we have of course that this is
equal to R the Omega
squar that goes to zero when R goes to
zero that's not surprising so did Row
squ The Omega squar but how about this
d^ squ what is that let's calculate that
let's calculate the relationship between
D and
Dr what is Dr D capital r d capital r is
equal to twice Row D row
right okay let's divide that and notice
that the
row is d r over twice
row now let's put in D Row squar D row
squ is
minus d r
2 divided by in this case it happens if
there's a four there the four is not the
interesting thing we could get rid of
the four by a trick but uh with row squ
row squ in the denominator
right everybody see what I did I just
wrote d r is equal to
Dr / two row and I stuck it into
there what is row squ row squ is r
forgetting about the four the four the
four we could actually soak up into a
into
a uh into
a change of units of R I simply actually
chose the wrong uh the wrong definition
I should have put a 1/2 in here or
something would have gotten rid of this
four but there it is let's look at this
metric this now has the the Omega squar
term goes to zero just like this one
does
at R equals z at R equals z it has the
same property as this namely something
goes to zero on the other hand look
what's happening over here also at R
equals z the coefficient of the Dr 2
term is getting
infinite what was in the numerator here
appears in the denominator here what's
in the numerator here appears in the
denominator over here
there's nothing pathological in the
SpaceTime over here I've just used some
pathological
coordinates which have the property that
the
metric has in terms of the time
component it has something which goes to
zero at R equals 0 and in terms of the
space component it has something which
goes to
Infinity there's something uh shall I
slow down here
okay everybody with me all
right so we see in
itself there's nothing pathological in
the space just because a coefficient
here goes to zero and a coefficient here
goes to Infinity in the same
way as I said the uh the relative four
which appears here is not the is not the
an important
issue now there's something else if we
looked at this metric here here and we
thought of r as our
coordinate notice what happens when R
goes from positive to
negative when R goes from positive to
negative this term becomes negative and
this term becomes
positive whatever R less than zero means
if it means anything at
all it has this interchange of space and
time just as this
does just as this does
so the question is can we understand
what R less than zero R is row squ how
can row squ be less than
zero okay the point is row s less than
zero is up in
here let's see if we can understand why
that
is each one of these hyperboloids or
hyperbolas corresponds to let's see what
it is it's
x^2 minus
t^2 equals row
SAR each one of these hyperbolas
corresponds to a different value of
row and precisely the same way as for a
circle we would have X2 + y^2 = Row 2
here we have x^2 - t ^2 = r^ 2 which
happens to be what I called
R also known as row
squ what happened when R got negative
look at this what happens when R gets
negative let's suppose R gets to be goes
from + one to
minus1 so x^2 - t ^2 = 1 that's a
hyperbola like this what happens when it
gets to be minus one
then it becomes x^2 - t ^2 =
-1 or t^2 - x^2 =
1 that's another hyperbola where is that
hyperbola 90 yeah that's a hyperbola up
here let's look at it right at this
point over here at that point over here
T is equal to 1 x is equal to 0 and t^2
- x^2 is equal to
one so it's not that anything crazy has
happened over here that space has become
time and time has become space or
anything like that it's just that the
coordinate that we're
using has a funny property let's think
about what let's think about what R
equals
0 Let's see R equals 0
means on this side over not R equals Zer
sorry um
not R equals
z uh yeah Omega equals Z Omega equals Z
Omega equals z is this line over
here okay that's what it is when R is
bigger than when R is positive when R is
negative it just becomes this line
here so it's crazy coordinates in which
what we're calling time makes a right
angle turn over here
all
right here's R here's Omega equals 1
Omega equals 1 looks like that and then
when it gets to this point it makes a
turn and it goes over
here so the main point here is that
coordinates if they're chosen in some
funny way can make it look like
something very dramatic is happening at
a point when in fact there's nothing
dramatic happening over
there it's just that we've chosen
coordinates that do funny
things okay how do we actually go
from yeah how do we actually go from
this metric is there some
approximation in which it is just this
metric over
here can we see some approximation in
which these two things are the same and
if we can we will have learned something
important about the black hole we would
have found an approximation certain
situations where the black hole is
really approximately flat SpaceTime
would that be how far your awak yeah not
yes that's
right right okay so let's
take this metric and Fiddle with it a
little bit we're going to be interested
in it very near the horizon
we're going to try to analyze it very
near the
Horizon near Ral 2
mg let's rewrite this this is Rus 2
mg over
R time dt^
2 minus Dr R
2 divided by or multiplied by r divided
by r 2
mg I've done nothing to get the r s no
we'll we'll do something with the r s
the Omega squar in a
minute all I've done was write 1 - 2 mg
/ R is r - 2 mg over R that's nothing at
all and now I'm interested in the
vicinity of the Horizon R very close to
2 mg well I can't set R equals to 2 mg
over here that's too extreme I I do want
to keep track of the fact that we're not
right at the Horizon but on the other
hand the r over
here there I can set it equal to 2 mg
near the
Horizon this doesn't as I move near the
Horizon a little closer a little further
R doesn't change very much let's suppose
R was a
kilometer and I move in and
out capital r r Schwarz Shield supposing
the Schwarz Shield Radius 2 mg is is a
kilometer and I move in and out by uh a
millimeter what happens to R well it
changes from a kilometer to a kilometer
plus a millimeter a negligible change in
R all right so I might as well over here
just write that R is equal to 2 mg and
that's a good
approximation I don't want to do it in
the
numerator because although R doesn't
change very much percentage wise Rus 2mg
does change a lot when I go from R from
uh near the Horizon um I can actually
change sign so I don't want to muddle
with this but in the denominator not
much happens when I change r a little
bit near the
Horizon likewise over here 2
mg that's a good approximation to the
metric very near the horizon
notice it still has the property that it
goes to zero when R goes to 2 mg and
this one goes to zero in the denominator
when R goes to 2
mg and I've made a small approximation
near the
Horizon now let's see what's going on
over here
minus r 2
again what we have is yeah we move in a
little bit closer or a little bit
further from the
Horizon r s doesn't change very
much it changes from a kilometer squar
to a kilm plus a millim squar it doesn't
change much and so very very close to
the Horizon we might as well call this
also 2
mg squared the Omega
squar okay we'll come back to this over
here this is what we're doing let me
tell you what we're doing here's here's
the Horizon of the black hole Ral 2 mg
we're interested in the
neighborhood of a point near the Horizon
I'm interested in what somebody sees who
moves in and out well if they move in
they don't move out again but if they're
moving a little bit near the vicinity of
this Horizon and they simply want to
blow this up they want to blow it up
look at it under a microscope and see
what the Horizon looks
like okay so apart from the pieces here
where we have to keep the difference
between R and 2mg we've simply set r
equal to
2mg now what's going on over here what
is the Omega squared if I look only in
the immediate vicinity of this point if
I look only in the immediate vicinity of
this point it's like looking at the
immediate vicinity of a point on a
sphere
a point on a sphere the immediate
vicinity of a point on a big sphere just
looks like a flat plane
right
right this whatever it
is it's a sphere of radius 2
mg that's what it is it's a sphere of
radius 2 mg as I move around on here but
a sphere of radius 2 mg it doesn't
matter how big the sphere is as long as
it's big enough when I move around on it
all I see is a flat plane so I can
actually replace this by a flat plane
it's just a tangent plane to the sphere
just like we replace the tangent plane
to the Earth by flat space the flat
space approximation it's not good for
the entire Horizon but it's good for the
neighborhood of the Horizon so actually
we can replace this by dy^
2 plus dz^2
the two coordinates this coordinate
here we call
whatever
R the other two coordinates I'm calling
Y and Z and this can just be called dy^
2 + dz^2 why because in the immediate
vicinity of a point it can be
approximated by a
plane if we approximate it by a plane
it's just D y^2 plus dz^2 so now we're
getting there we have
the metric right at that point in the
immediate vicinity of that point here it
is our - 2 mg over 2
mg the R 2 2 mg over r - 2 mg
and the other pieces of it very simple
almost uh
trivial just dx2 + d y^
2 DX s minus D sorry dz^2 + d y^ 2
now I just want to emphasize this is not
the exact metric of the black hole it is
the metric of a piece of space very
close to a particular Point what we're
trying to find out is what is actually
going on in a small neighborhood of that
Horizon is there something nasty and
vicious because R is going to 2mg or is
it more like this over here where there
was in fact nothing nasty or vicious
going on it was just a flat region of
flat space flat space
time okay so this has vague
similarities where's I with
this something in the numerator the same
thing in the denominator a factor of
four which I wasn't very careful to I
could have defined as I said I could
have defined things in a way to get rid
of it I didn't so there it
is okay let's change
coordinates again now this whole game is
a game of changing coordinates until you
find coordinates where you recognize
what's going on where you recognize with
some Simplicity what's going on I don't
want to change to this capital r
coordinate this capital r coordinate was
just a contrivance to show you that
there are situations where a numerator
of one thing can become the will be the
denominator of the other when this goes
to Z this one goes to Infinity that was
just a contrivance to make it look as
much as possible like this but I'm
really more interested in the original
polar coordinates
here here's the original polar
coordinates and my claim is that by a
smart change of
variables I can
make this metric over here these two
pieces of it look exactly the same as
this
close to the Horizon all right how can
we do
that well the trick is to realize what
row is row is the proper distance from
this point over
here spatial distance it's the proper
distance how do I know what the proper
distance D
for move out along
here the Omega is equal to zero if I
move
horizontally and the d d is just equal
to minus d^ s is minus d r^
s that's definition of proper distance
along
here
okay
um let's see if we can find the proper
distance from The
Horizon to an arbitrary point R here's
an arbitrary point R and then use that
to replace the coordinate R the proper
distance from the r from The Horizon to
that point I want to use that as a new
variable I'll call it row
again how do we find the proper distance
from this point over here which is Ral 2
mg to an arbitrary point
R well anybody have a suggestion plug in
zero for the other
yeah yeah we'll plug in zero for the
other coordinates but then we have to do
a little bit of
work yeah we're going to move
out straight out without changing time
without changing X or without changing Z
and and Y and see how much proper
distance there is between here and here
the proper distance is determined by
this ter in the metric if we move out
without changing time and without
changing DZ and D y then the proper
distance that we move out let's call it
DS DS squ is the same as DT d^ squ
except with a minus sign the proper
distance d s squ is just equal to Dr R
2 * 2
mg over r - 2
mg okay we take a square root of that
now how do we find the
distance from this point to that
point we have to do an
integral the distance is the integral of
this okay this is the differential
distance when you change R by a little
bit if we actually want the
distance from Ral 2 mg to an arbitary
point we have to integrate
so let's call that integral row it's the
proper distance to an arbitrary point
and it's the integral D
R square otk of 2 mg that's a constant
that comes out divided r - 2 mg Square
Ro
TK here we
are this is the proper distance where do
we integrate from we integrate sorry
this is uh Dr the
r we integrate from R yeah from R equals
mg to
R I'm going to stop for questions at
this point because this is quite
critical to understanding what's going
on but
uh Ah that's just the point
R okay let's call this r Prime the
integration
variable
right right and we integrate from R = 2
mg to the moving point or to the uh
arbitrary point R right R outside the
Horizon to be
specific okay can anybody do well let's
first of all just take the 2 mg outside
the integral that's easy that part is
easy H yes there's a 2mg of
course uh so we take out the 2 mg in the
numerator
here and we have an integral to
do it's a square root integral it's a
simple square root integral it's one/
square root of something and what's the
integral of one/ square root
uh yeah who can do one / square root X
to Theus 12
integrated what is that it's x to the
3es uh sorry x to the + one2
and then uh two
uh yeah
two
right the integral of x the -2 is T
X2 how do I prove that I differentiate
this I get X-2 and 1 12 * 2 is 1 good
okay so here we are Row the
distance between the Horizon and a point
R
is given
by uh did I
lose I think I
did you're absolutely
right right we have to take the square
root of this whole
thing good thank you there a square root
of 2 mg that was in the numerator and
then a square root of R primeus 2 mg in
the denominator the square root came
from taking the square root of uh d s
squ the R square root square root okay
so what do we have we have then that row
is equal to
twice that's the two from here then
there's the square root of 2
mg that's from here and then the square
root in the
numerator Square < TK of r - 2 mg
where I've plugged in the end
point into the
integral that's
row again what is it it's the proper
distance from The Horizon to an
arbitrary point at distance r
it's also a change of
variables it's also a change of
variables where we've where I have now
imagin a change of variables which I
substitute for the variable
R the Schwarz Shield coordinate R I
substitute the coordinate row notice is
a square root let's see did we have uh
if you
remember R was equal to row s
s uh again there was a variable over
here which was related to a variable
over here by a square root row is equal
to the square root of R here we have row
related to the square Ro T of r - 2
mg so they do look similar okay let's
let's rewrite the
metric let's rewrite the metric it's a
bit of a nuisance it's not very hard I'm
taking you through all the steps I could
just write down the answer but I want to
take you through the
steps here we are new coordinate
coordinate transformation to proper
distance which is just equal to to
square < TK of 8
mg I got the eight by bringing the two
inside Time Square
t of r - 2
mg that's the proper distance from The
Horizon and all we have to do now to
rewrite the
is to well we have to figure out what it
is first of all row over 8
mg is Rus 2 mg is square root of r - 2
mg so let's Square
it sorry square root
right that's row ided by square root of
mg is equal to the square root of what's
on this side
okay let's Square
it row
SAR ided by 8
mg is equal to r - 2 mg well that's
convenient because we have r - 2mg all
over the place in this metric
here so it's convenient that we know
what R minus 2 mg
is let's now rewrite the metric
first of all there's this
term I realize that this is a tedious uh
thing to sit through you don't need to
sit through it you can do it yourself
but let's do it uh
together all right here we are r - 2 mg
over 2 mg well here it is Rus 2 mg is
Row 2 over 8
mg then I believe there's another 2 mg
down squares that makes that 16
M2 G2
right times
what time dt^ 2
right now what about this monstrosity
over
here anybody there's a quick answer to
this a really quick answer to
it what it is in terms of
row
anybody yeah but then we'd have to also
convert D Dr to D row all right what was
the definition of
row no no the definition was the proper
distance from The
Horizon if row is the proper distance
from The
Horizon then this is just D
squ it is the proper distance from The
Horizon the way we got row was basically
writing that d r^ 2 is Dr r^ 2 over 2 mg
is just equal to this thing here so we
don't have any work to do to figure out
the Row part of the metric it is
just the row
squ it is the proper distance minus
minus
minus minus got all thex the z^2 and the
y^ S which go along for the ride
we're almost
there what are we comparing this with
let's go back where is my rindler metric
my polar coordinate metric my polar
coordinate metric was Row 2 D Omega
SAR minus d^ 2 and if there were other
coordinates coming out of the
Blackboard if there were other
coordinates coming out of the Blackboard
then we would put them in by hand minus
dz^2 minus dy^
2 is this the same as
this not quite what's the
difference 16 mg^
s okay but now there's a simple thing we
can do we can just make a change another
change of
variables
namely let D Omega
equal or just let
Omega equal T over 4
mg Omega
squar is well let's just do D Omega D
Omega is equal to 1 4
mg DT and guess what the Omega squar is
just DT ^2 over 16 m^2 G ^2 so I just
look at this say oh my goodness this is
nothing
but d t over
4mg
squared and so all I have to do is
change variables from T to
Omega and this becomes row s the Omega
squ blah blah blah the same thing as
this
here okay so let's just go through what
I did again without actually doing it
I changed well the first thing I did was
I approximated near the Horizon it's
called the near Horizon
approximation and it's not just the near
Horizon it's near a specific point on
the
horizon we substituted for 1 - 2 mg / r
r - 2 mg/ R and then said R is
approximately equal to 2
mg so that just gave us
a simple expression over here same thing
upside down over here and then this
metric on the sphere was approximated by
the tangent space which just means it's
the same operation as when I do on the
surface of the Earth I use X and Y um
for a small patch on the farmer's field
he doesn't need to keep track of the
curvature of the Earth he just needs X
and Y or north and east or whatever and
uses the flat space
metric okay that was the first step
simplify this
way next step was to compute the proper
distance that
corresponds in other words really simply
stated it was just setting d^ 2/ 2 mg *
R just equal to d^
2 and figure out what row is let's write
it that
way let's just think of it that way
Dr Square < TK of 2
mg/ r - 2 mg = d r definition of
d I took the square root of this square
root of this square root of this and
then I integrated to find out that row
was nothing but where is it here it
is that gave me a new coordinate row
which simplifi this term the main point
was it simplified this term why did it
simplify it well Dr times this piece of
stuff over here is just equal to D so
this just becomes D
Squared this on the other hand was also
not too complicated it just turned out
to be row squar ided 16
M
G2 why
what who said D R equals d r
yeah I didn't say that D row squ is
equal to Dr R 2 * 2 mg R 2G
side it again second
right right there you the
yeah yeah but you didn't replace d r s
with that no no I didn't I replaced Dr r
s divided by this right okay look here
we
are let's let's go back one more step do
it once more here we have this Dr 2 over
1 - 2
mg
well 2
mg over Rus 2 mg okay whoever asked the
question are you happy with that I
didn't do anything I just rewrote it I'm
setting that equal to d^ S now you can't
ask me why afterwards why d s is equal
to this it just
is okay definition of d squ i take the
square root of both
sides and I integrate to find out that
row is equal to
this now there's no question that this
thing over here is equal to just the row
squ it's the way it was
defined it was just a trick to redefine
a coordinate to simplify this thing over
here that's all can always do it you can
always make a change of variables to
change uh from Dr to d r where by
definition Dr R times the square root
here is equal to D okay
so by the time we're finished we get
back to
here well that's pretty
interesting it tells us what does it
tell
us it tells us that the
geometry the near Horizon geometry very
near this point is really no
different than the geometry of flat
SpaceTime in polar
coordinates you can't tell the
difference very very close to the
Horizon of a black
hole you can't tell the difference
between flat space and the black hole
number one number two this row variable
which was proper distance from The
Horizon and which enters into the
metric
in this form over
here is
obviously close to the horizon
the same
variable as the accelerated coordinate
system uses to distinguish one Observer
from the other just the ray or I don't
know what to call it the variable from
one coordinate to another so the Horizon
of the black
hole The Horizon of the black hole and
different observers stationed at
different
distances are just like the The
Observers stationed at different
distances in the accelerated reference
frame why accelerated because gravity
and acceleration are the same thing if I
station somebody over here near the
Horizon of the black hole my stationer I
mean hold them there hold them there by
a uh rope around the
neck they're going to be they're going
to feel like they're being pulled
they're going to feel like they're being
accelerated in that direction the
further out we are the less the
acceleration the less stretching of the
neck same thing
here to keep somebody on one of these
accelerated coordinate systems you might
imagine pulling them along by a rope
around their neck the closer they are to
the Horizon
here the harder you have to pull them so
it's exactly the
same geometry the near Horizon geometry
is is the accelerated coordinate system
geometry course it's all it is is good
old flat SpaceTime but the coordinates
in this region here
are not 10 after n no I keep making keep
making mistake right okay it's time
dilation near a black hole something
like that it's going too
fast okay so that uh
that what does it tell us it tells us
that as I said repeat it over and over
again the Horizon of the black hole is
not a singular place now in particular
again the fact that the relative sign
change between here and here that makes
it look like space becomes Time and Time
becomes space there's nothing really
happening what it corresponds to to see
what it corresponds to we have to go
back to that capital r coordinate and
I'll just remind you the capital r
coordinate which was r
equal row s is that what it was yeah the
metric in terms of that was R dt^ 2
minus and there was a silly 1 over4 that
doesn't mean anything uh R
downstairs the uh the
r the r
s so that's very much like what's going
on here
yeah if on this side of
the black board the uh The Accelerated
object get closer and closer to the
horiz but never gets Infinity not amount
of time same on this side of so how does
get into a black
[Music]
hole all I can do is point you to this
diagram from somebody looking from
outside
this line
here is Omega equals infinity
right Omega Z 1 2 3 4 Omega equals
infinity out there from the Reckoning of
the accelerated coordinate system first
of all nothing passes The Horizon until
Omega equals infinity and furthermore
somebody watching they can wait forever
and ever they go way out here that's a
long time in the future according to
this fellow here he looks back and he
still doesn't see anything having
crossed the Horizon here it is here's
the Horizon it looks way
back at even after a very long time he
may be close to that Horizon he looks he
has not crossed it he looks back and he
sees poor Alice uh having not yet cross
the Horizon now
um exactly the same thing happens
here exactly the same
thing and this is the picture to come to
when you're uh when
you're all right now there is a
difference there is a difference the
difference is far from The Horizon far
from The
Horizon the metrics are quite different
close to the Horizon it looks like good
old flat space but flat space in these
strange accelerated coord
coordinates and strange I mean they have
a singularity over here time is this
hyperbolic angle but far
away when R is very
large this is small 2 mg over R is
negligible 2 mg over R is negligible and
it just looks again like flat space but
flat space in which time is time and SP
R which with ordinary coordinates R and
T so there's a transition from very
close to the Horizon where it looks like
flat space in polar coordinates to very
far away where it just looks like flat
space in ordinary coordinates far away
you would not be tempted to call T A
hyperbolic angle but close in to the
Horizon t or at least T over 4 mg where
is it t over 4 mg Omega was T over 4 mg
yes T over 4 mg close in becomes a
hyperbolic angle so there's a a
characterist a characteristic difference
in these coordinates close to the
Horizon and far from The Horizon I can
give you
a well I won't give you another analogy
for it it'll just get confusing any Ober
they are as as something in Falls
towards the Event Horizon doesn't matter
how far where close it is close
continuous um no one will ever see it
actually get be memorized nobody who
stays outside the black hole how close
you get so unless you're at the event
horizon or inside the Event Horizon no
one will ever
see enter the black hole how can a black
hole ever get
larger because nothing ever goes into it
it gets larger by depositing its
energy very very close to the horizon
and causing the Horizon to grow a little
bit it's it's questionable whether you
should distinguish the stuff which is
very close to the Horizon from The
Horizon itself The Horizon grows not
because anything goes into the black
hole it just merges with the Horizon and
what is what is that distance can it be
Artic yeah it's a plunk
distance does that relate to this
or no no at some point as you watch
imagine imagine what happens as you
watch something fall through the Horizon
that something is sending out signals
all right it's sending out radio signals
or sending out no let's say it's sending
out
um uh light let's see if we can see what
happens what's observed from the
outside we can do it by drawings or we
can do it by equations I prefer to do it
by
drawings why did you radio signal what's
that why did you give up on radio
signals oh because radio signals I want
to start with something shorter
wavelength and then get the longer and
longer wavelength radio there's nothing
longer than I don't know any name for a
thing longer than a radio signal so if I
want to start with something short
wavelength I'll start with what did I
say Optical light Optical light what
comes after Optical light uh infrared
after infrared is microwaves after
microwaves and so forth I wanted to have
a range that I could uh talk about
okay
so let's uh first yeah let's
um so here's Alice Alice is going in and
she's sending out in her own reference
frame she's got a little oscillating
dipole which is sending out light a
little Atomic dipole which is
oscillating and here are the
oscillations one oscillation per unit of
proper time in some units which is
appropriate to the emission of light so
a wave Crest from here a trough from
here a Crest from here a trough from
here and so forth and the that's Alice
here's
Bob and Alice is sending out I wish I
had another color I don't have another
let me see if I do have another
color
no and I'm not going to leave these
psychologists my pins
okay so let's see what Bob
sees Bob sees a wave the first wave hit
him over here the second wave hits him
over here the third wave hits him over
here the 25th wave hits from over
here how much proper
time is there
between the waves at they hit bob that
gets drawn out longer and longer one way
to see it is just to say that Bob is
receding and therefore Doppler
shift from this point of view there's no
real difference between Doppler shift
and gravitational red
shift as Alice gets closer and closer to
the Horizon here she sends out waves and
the last wave that she sends
out over here gets to Bob at a very very
late stretched out
time if the waves actually have finite
frequency then there's going to be a
basically a last wave that she
sends this means that Bob sees
Alice more and more red shifted she's
sending out light signals but Bob sees
after a short amount of time or a
certain amount of time he's receding
away and he sees
infrared then he sees
microwave then he sees radio waves of a
meter and then he sees radio waves of a
kilometer and then he sees radio waves
of a million kilometers and radio waves
with a million
kilometers don't have very much energy
they're sending out you know one Photon
or some number of photons per unit time
Alice is sending out Bob is receiving
those photons slower and slower and
their longer and longer wavelengths so
the energy that he's receiving is
getting lower and
lower what he sees is Alice's dipole
slowing down in fact everything about
Alice because he sees it through light
he sees slowing
down um and you don't need black holes
to see it you just see it from this
picture
here that uh that Bob sees Alice slowing
down and slowing down and slowing down
and finally she sends out her last
wave okay why is it the last wave well
if she had higher frequencies she could
fit some more in
there and yet higher frequencies she
could fit even more in there but with
any finite frequency oscillated to send
out the rate of the radiation there's
going to be a last wave that she sends
out and then Bob doesn't see her anymore
she's
gone as far as Bob is concerned what
does happen is the remnant of Alice
is um is merged with the Horizon and in
fact makes the black hole a little bit
bigger now to see that we would have to
solve Einstein's equations with
infalling material and so forth that's a
little bit hard uh and but it's easy so
the longest wavelength that she puts out
the size of the black hole you
put that's about no that's that's right
the longest W you can put out is about
the size of the black
hole does see Bob slowing down okay so
does Alice see Bob what Alice sees is
Bob receding away and moving closer and
closer to the speed of light now when
something goes past you with a speed of
light yes it is slowed down it's slowed
down by Loren contraction so yes Alice
watching Bob well yes okay Alice
watching
Bob sees Bob recede away and therefore
yes slow down there's a problem for
Alice though this is the near Horizon
geometry and we haven't talked about
what
happens at R equals z something really
bad happens at R equals 0 that is not a
coordinate
Singularity if we were to calculate the
curvature in particular let's say the
curvature scalar well no not the
curvature scaler some some measure of
the curvature of this
geometry we would find there's nothing
radical happening at the Horizon but at
R equals 0 remember R equals
0 was the place where let's go back to
Newton what happens at R equals
0 gravity becomes infinite um tidal
forces become infinite right if we
calculate the tidal forces associated
with this thing here we would find they
become infinite at R equals 0 okay so R
equals 0 is a real genuine Singularity a
place where curvature becomes import uh
infinite it's a place where tidal forces
become infinite it is not a place which
is anything like flat space but the
question is where is it on this diagram
let's let's redraw the diagram and try
to figure out
where you
said the mass
inside what's that tell me what
the inside of where you are theide where
you are yeah but now we've had a
complete gravitational collapse and C
collaps to a
point coll to a
[Music]
point don't go that to Alice
but Al isn't
here is
right right
right right Alice yeah Alice she went
right behind the black hole I have a
question Alice has some friends having a
conversation doesn't matter which
direction they are relative to each
other they just have a
conversation well Bob Bob they both
following freely Alice and her friends
are all following freely through the
yeah they just talk to each other just
as if nothing was happening until they
get near the
singularity yeah if if one friend is
ahead of the other then they can't talk
then and put it in the other what's that
say again if one is a little ahead of
the other and they can't communicate
when one gets behind the garage the
other still be no okay so let's let's
Analyze That
here they are they're both falling okay
they're communicating back and forth
freely nothing funny happening now it is
true that once Alice here's Alice and
here's
Shirley Alice is ahead of Shirley she's
fallen in first here she
is just as she gets near the Horizon she
sends a signal out to Shirley Shirley
gets the signal once she passes The
Horizon
she cannot get a signal to the Shirley
who is before the Horizon there's no way
she can get a signal from here to here
but you can get a signal from here to
here even if there was no black hole she
couldn't have gotten the signal from
here to here that would have exceeded
the speed of light so Alice sends
Shirley signals sherley sends Alice
signals nothing funny about them
now if Shirley would have decided not to
go into the black hole at the last
minute here she is and then she decides
not to go into the black hole not to
cross the Horizon but to get onto one of
these accelerated
trajectories maybe she was connected to
the space station by a cable and the
cable only let her go down so far and
then got pulled taught she supported
away from the horizon then Alice can see
Shirley but Shirley cannot see Alice
behind the Horizon there's no way she
can see behind the Horizon so if Shirley
freely Falls her relationship to Alice
is Not Unusual back and forth they can
communicate if Shirley the last minute
decides not to fall through the Horizon
then indeed Alice falls out of
her experience
yeah so uh the type of uh ionization
doesn't occur at the Horizon what type
of thing atoms don't ionize at the
Horizon um well now you talk now we're
getting into quantum mechanics which
we're not going to do this quarter but
uh um the the atams IIs near the horiz
that depends on who's watching
them if if an object is moving along
these y or
DZ which means kind of moving right on
right on that
surface would it
continue moving
there no it will fall into the
Horizon but if space is flat there it
should kind of keep being flat yeah the
problem is that these trajectories that
move along here are going to be space
like and why is that supposing supposing
we have a trajectory very close to the
Horizon okay that's moving with a DX or
sorry a Dy or a
DZ okay so let's see so that means Dy or
DZ is not equal to zero right but we're
extremely close to the Horizon let's say
practically at the Horizon then this
term is zero and this term is
zero oh sorry well this term is zero
because Dr is equal to zero
we're not moving in and out we're only
moving along the horizon
right okay so this one's not there
because Dr is equal to zero along that
motion and this one's zero because the
coefficient of DT is equal to
Zer second one Z over
Z we're we're slightly away from the
Horizon slightly away from the Horizon
just outside okay but the main thing is
Dr is exactly equal to zero with
skirting The Horizon at a fixed r that
was the question if you skirt The
Horizon at a fixed r that means this is
exactly
zero all right and R minus 2 mg is just
a small number on the other hand this is
not zero but it's very very small in
particular the coefficient here is so
small that if D if we if we get close
enough if we get close enough this will
eventually get smaller than DZ so if we
make a little Excursion along DZ here by
a given
distance no matter how long we take to
do it if we're close enough to the
Horizon this term is zero that means the
trajectory here is spacelike and it
means it's exceeding the speed of light
so anything that tries to skirt along
the horizon is exceeding the speed of
light and that's because time has slowed
down so much or the coefficient of the
DT squ has slowed down so much that the
trajectory becomes space likee you
understand the difference you understand
what space like trajectory is right so
skirting along the horizon is forbidden
motion it's motion faster than the speed
of
light
uh supposing all right let's talk about
a thing well I I think that'll that'll
do it right so you can skirt along the
horizon like
that uh
let's get to the singularity now the
singularity is at R equals 0 here now
let's remember the
connection R equals z or r equals small
let's take small values of R for small
values of R that's where the in change
between positive and negative has taken
place okay for small values of
R we're in
here small values of R don't correspond
fixed values of R don't
correspond
to Tim like
trajectories trajectories of observers
but they correspond to space likee
surfaces like this this just to see
what's going on let's go back to this
metric over
here supposing R if R is positive then
we're on the outside if R is negative
we're on the
inside all right so here's the inside
here's the outside in this case r being
negative it's different than little r
being negative here it's like r - 2 mg
being
negative Big R is like r - 2 m g all
right when Big R changes
sign the
hyperboloids x^2 - t ^2 =
R
become hyperboloids like
this so fixed R outside corresponds to
the motion of an accelerated Observer
inside it corresponds to a kind of
space-like
surface another way to say it is fixed R
inside the back hole is some time not
some
place it's a time and not a place fixed
R okay now what about R equals
z well r equal Z is sort of like capital
r equal
negative as I said Rus 2 mg is sort of
like capital
r what does r equal something negative
correspond to it corresponds to a
surface like
this so little r equal 0 is a Surface
like this this is little R equals z like
that that's the
singularity and it's not a place so much
as it is a time once you fall through
here notice once you fall through here
you have no way of avoiding this
Singularity the speed of light is 45°
angles you cannot move faster than the
speed of light when you're out here and
you send a light Ray in the outward
Direction it might Escape if you send it
in the inward Direction it might hit the
singularity will hit the
singularity if you're inside it doesn't
matter which direction you send the
light Ray in you're going to be the
singularity yeah if you're free falling
there's no reason for you to use these
funny coordinates well Free Falling just
means you're moving
lines you don't have to use any
coordinates here's the geometry the
whole idea that the time x and
coordinates have switch is because of
these funny
coordinates the coordinates are funny
but the geometry this is the
geometry this this picture doesn't
require let's take the r equal Z away
that's it that's the
geometry that's the geometry that's what
it looks like I don't need to put any
coordinates on it that's what it looks
like like and once you're in here you
can't escape falling into the
singularity here agree it's the whole
idea of switching well I keep telling
you time and space don't interchange
it's just you've drawn coordinate axes
which make a right angle turn so
basically everything is other than
except for title effects the Free
Falling Observer doesn't nothing
yeah so at a certain proper time that's
it at a certain proper time you've
crossed the
Horizon but crossing the Horizon is not
in itself a dangerous event you're
doomed but you're not you have
particular specifi proper time and then
you will
reach right you might not be going at
that 45
angle if you just fall in and you pass
the Horizon you have some particular
amount of time left over yeah yeah yeah
that's right the maximum amount of time
that you have is basically approximately
equal to the time that it takes to cross
the Horizon of a black hole it's just a
numerical
fact uh if you
measure distances and time in the same
units C equals 1 then the Schwarz Shield
radius becomes a
Time Schwarz Shield radius of a star
would be about a meter that's a
kilometer excuse me light
takes seconds to cross a kilometer one
one over uh 1 over 3 * 10
5th so it's the diameter it doesn't
matter order of magnitude order of
magnitude order of magnitude it takes
about one transer time across the black
hole and then you're in
the and then once you're there
that's I don't know what to say once
you're there
can we say any more about that no
no everything becomes infinitely dense
infinitely distorted infinitely uh
quantum mechanics becomes important
everything is torn apart into its
constituents and worse and uh we're into
a real Terra
Incognito but really you never going to
get far enough to experience that
Singularity and so yeah
does the singularity
actually does the infinity actually
exist in real life or is it is there
something happen right before you get
there that sort of uh mitigates that
fact or CL or something like that well
nobody really knows nobody really knows
my own feeling is no it's it's it's an
ultimate end of uh things but but let's
put it this way uh let's just say nobody
really knows but but we know how to
follow it for example into a region
where the curvature might be uh the
radius of curvature might be no bigger
than the radius of a proton easy to
follow it there nothing uh we we know
very very well what the physics is like
down to those
distances so you would not like to be
squeezed into a radius equal to the size
of a proton actually yeah the tital
forces would be of that magnitude that
they would
uh so does this mean that sense of
impact really with with a large mass
with the Horizon there's no sense of
impact with the
Horizon there is something Dreadful that
happens at the singularity but the
singularity as I said is not so much a
place a singularity if the singularity
was a place a spot over here and you're
falling in well you could go around it
if the singularity is the end of time as
I've drawn here there's no way to avoid
it uh
so there is something I should tell you
about real about genuine black holes you
would not survive the transit across the
Horizon of a stellar Mass black hole the
tidal forces are just too large if you
were to estimate and this is a Newtonian
calculation if you were to take a
stellar mass and compress it down to the
size of a um of a uh uh compress it to
the size of a black hole which would be
about a kilometer well a kilometer
doesn't seem very small it seems like
you could pass through it safely but the
tidal forces just the gradient of the
gravitational field would uh you know
squeeze you out like a toothpaste
through a so that would be it would be
very dramatic going through the Horizon
of a uh on the other hand if you as
small as a
parium then the gravitational gradients
across your body would be negligible and
you would fall right through the Horizon
without uh without any
trouble um similarly if we took a black
hole which was I don't know a billion
solar masses a billion solar
masses The Horizon is so big and so flat
that the tidal forces are
not very strong on your body at a
billion solar masses it's a little bit
um how shall I
say little bit counterintuitive you
might think the bigger the mass of the
black hole the worse it is to go through
the Horizon of of the black hole but
that's not true the point is that the
bigger the mass of the black hole the
bigger the Horizon and the less curved
and the less tidal forces the less you
would be squeezed going through the
horizon so if a black
hole were a billion solar masses you
would go through the Horizon pretty
easily I think I once estimated I can't
remember whether let's see a billion
solar masses
so
uh it's a billion uh billion kilome how
long how long does it take to go a
billion
kilometers about an hour
right is that right billion billion k is
like the radius of the solar
system yeah about radius of solar system
which is about a light hour so right so
with the biggest black holes that I
found at the centers of the biggest
galaxies you could probably last for
half an hour or something like that
after falling through the Horizon not
longer than that uh that's how much time
it would take light to go across it take
a black hole of a trillion uh solar
masses there are no such things probably
there are no such things you would last
another thousand times
longer so uh going through the Horizon
of a black hole for a stellar Mass black
hole is not as innocent as I've made it
sound um but the principle is there a
sufficiently small living creature would
survive going through the Horizon even
of a solar mass black wouldn't last very
long hit the singularity in a fraction
of a second but still it would be at the
singularity not at the
Horizon okay um
I don't know are there any anything left
to uh
yeah I want to ask you a question about
the coordinates the the coordinates
we've been using correspond to a series
of rods and clocks yes that are outside
that are F that are what
that that are that are fixed locations
outside the black hole they're not
moving with respect to the black hole so
whereas The View that we're seeing of
the accelerated coordinates is a series
of rods and clocks which are
under relative to relative
to okay I
[Music]
know accelerated relative to what
yeah relative to Alice okay now if Alice
falls through the Horizon of a black
hole believe me Bob is accelerated
relative what I'm talking about is the
is the the understanding of the
coordinates over up up near the black
hole we're assuming that the that the
that the we have a bunch of points
scattered around in a small cube and
they're clocks there and they're running
now when you get inside the black you
can't do that actually on the surface of
the black hole itself you can't stand
there yeah but but you could extend that
coordinate system across the boundary of
the black hole and you still get a
series of points and the and
clocks and the clocks are still
measuring time are they not very
very the time the slows down
there's nothing to prevent you in this
picture over here from using a set of
coordinates and related to real clocks
and rods which look like
that all right this is um Alice's freely
falling reference frame kind of like to
draw that picture over here on this side
okay it's just a reference frame which
freely falls through the Horizon of the
black
hole okay and the and the but the the
one we're talking about with the t's and
rs is one which doesn't freely pull for
black that's right that's the one that
looks like
this yeah in order to use and and it it
looks like that on outside the black
hole right
and and inside the black hole if we just
extend the coordinates they look like
this okay right so we can we can imagine
a series of rods and Frames which
actually extends across imagine but
they'd have to be
falling you cannot imagine anything
standing still behind the
Horizon why
notss to what the what the variables are
predicting anything that's standing
still that means that a fixed R fixed
little r you can't move along one of
those coordinates the way you were able
to move along these coordinates because
those coordinates are
space if you Tred to make something at a
fixed R here it would be exceeding the
speed of
light something at a fixed R behind the
Horizon is exceeding the speed of light
but isn't that what the r is that what
the r refers to in that in that equation
something which is exceeding the
yes right behind the Horizon it's
exceeding the spe yeah so no there can't
be rods which
are go through here with these rods just
standing still statically
they're they're going so so it's so it's
basically a notional coordinate system
that you can't imagine actually
constructing no well you can imagine
constructing it but in here the things
that would measure R would be
clocks and the things which would
measure let's see this is this was time
the time coordinate becomes a coordinate
like
that so behind the Horizon these but
they only only coordinates keep in mind
that they're rather arbitrary we've just
drawn some coordinates behind the
Horizon if you wanted to measure R you
would use clocks and if you wanted to
measure T you'd use meter
sticks all
right T flows along here the same
coordinate same mathematical coordinate
flows along here you measure things in
here with meter sticks
Einstein well keep in mind this is not a
problem of general relativity this is a
problem of special
relativity this is just ordinary flat
SpaceTime no gravitating objects except
as seen by an observer who is um being
pulled along at a constant
acceleration what the the one thing
which is not there in that case would be
that Singularity The Singularity is
really the gravitating object right that
uh that's the real
signal that there's uh title forces for
example can we go back to the way back
to where the metric comes from
it was soltion it was a solution to
equation starting from some distribution
of energy of mass any that's right or
what distribution of mass is start
any any as long as it's closed within
here right all right so we start with
Einstein's equations make some
assumptions I'll tell you what
assumptions we first start Ein equation
r-
[Music]
G now or some foure pi and H and G's and
and that now we're studying a region
outside of a place where there is any
energy
distribution and that means that we're
studying the solutions to this
equation knowing full well that inside
here there may be some material but
outside here sorry G
R equals
zero those are Einstein's equations in
the absence of any
matter it's exactly the same as Newton
Newton you would write Del s of the
potential equals the energy distribution
matter distribution Mass distribution
and outside Mass distrib rtion you would
write
zero you know that inside something's
happening but outside there's nothing
happening and so you ask what are the
general Solutions of this equation under
certain conditions all right so I'll
tell you what the conditions are what
are the general Solutions of this
equation which are radially symmetric in
other words which are only a function of
r let's let's start with this one what
is the general solution of the equation
L =
0 where 5 is only a function of r and
not a function of theta 5 and time for
example well is a
[Music]
general
it one other one other restriction and
that is a solution um one of the
Restriction by go to zero far
away I goes to zero far away you just
told me in fact what the general
solution is ax² b y well quadratic form
that's uh no no no no a linear form
quadratic form not constant on the right
side really but assuming also that it
goes to zero far away well the answer is
are n there are no Solutions of this
equation where five goes to zero far
away way but now supposing you say what
are the solutions to this
equation outside a certain Sphere not
caring whether you solve the equations
on the
inside not worrying about whether you
solve the equations on inside but only
caring about what you if you solve the
equations on the outside then there are
solutions the Gen only one form of
solution the one form of the solution is
that Pi is a Conant
R only mathematical
solution now what determines this
constant in the real world ter the
constant is the mass contained within
that
sphere so it's
mg minus sign the physics tells you that
it's a minus sign and the
NG is
um that's the most General solution of
equation of L2 5 = 0 if you don't care
if the equation is solved by the
ins now supposing we take this here uh I
sort of understood this answer but I was
going to then ask M was what happened to
the mask
inside well let's let's continue to
follow look we can think we can ask what
happens if we think a very small
sphere well the answer is exactly the
same except the mass is inside that
small sphere someplace what happens if
you go to the limit of a point particle
and the equation is satisfied everywhere
except at the point where the where the
point particle is where the point
particle is there's a singularity that's
where R is equal to
zero okay so what and if you like you
can think of the mass as falling in and
all accumulating at a
point a point of space
where is the material that falls into a
black
hole it's on here it falls
in ultimately Ares on the singularity
The Singularity is also Ral Z so all the
material I fill
in is located in some sense at Ral 0 but
Ral 0 is now space line and not time
line
so where is the material it's here
insist that being our equal
zero everywhere's outside of here which
means everywhere's out of
here Einstein's equations are solv with
zero right hand side the only place
where there's a source over
here but that's the end of time anyway
that's just a
singularity for for Newton it's also a
singularity a very different
character uh does that answer the
question um much an answer okay so what
prevents
usoni Sim you will that eventually
things
repel what prevents Theon
yeah yeah
um that's that's that's a fair question
so is there something in is it there
something
in in here that's preventing the
singular same there is a very
interesting history with this
question it was
known it was known I don't know how far
back it
was that um a bunch of mass
points in neonian physics will not
collapse to a point will not collapse to
a
singularity or let's put it this way
it's a real set measures zero initial
conditions which allows it to collapse
to a singularity and the reason is just
the tiniest bit of angular momentum of
one particle relative to the other will
have them miss each
other just a little B bit of angular
momentum will provide enough Sy of pce
that they
will so unless they are
really very very symmetrically
distributed with no angular momentum at
all they will just go past each other
and come and
uh miss each other and not form a
singularity this was known this was a
heum about classical mechanics because
of it Einstein assumed that a black hole
could never form he assumed that somehow
the same thing would happen and it would
be impossible is that the same thing
that makes globular clusters basically
stable as a whole I mean they live for a
long time they do live for a long time
it's different
here I I'll come
here just take a single point particle
supposed it was suppose there was for a
moment a singularity in neonian physics
Point
par and then you throw another one in
unless you happen it's a point this a
point
part unless you're Happ to aim it with
infinite Precision it will miss this
point and just go back
out what happens here what happens here
once a particle passes The Horizon
there's no way that it can escape hting
that's because the singularity of
different character It's the End of Time
rather than being a pointless space so
Einstein was wrong his logic was wrong
you had the picture that the singularity
is a point
and that anything that tries to add some
Mass to it will miss it and go back
out whereas The Singularity is a real
cck he didn't understand the idea of a
horizon and the Horizon was really a
point of no return that once you passed
it you would you mean it's not good
enough just have a collapsing star
providing a lot of
pressure to drive
everything inward classically I
mean yeah
the thing I don't understand is well
this pre presupposes that there's a
singularity begin doesn't it because
otherwise the whole argument gave that
otherwise electrons are
singularities I mean it's not clear from
this exists a singularity I'm saying
maybe by observation I'm saying even if
there were a
singularity you couldn't add to
it even if there was so even if you
could get one started and had one you
couldn't add to it if you can't add to
one having one started obviously you
can't make
one but let's say in terms of face space
the picture Chang from classical picture
to later on the Quant mechanical picture
when you look at the incompressibility
of pH space the incompressibility is
there because of PL constant which
suggests no the incompressibility is
there because of Le of those
the incompressibility face
[Music]
SP right keep going because you're
asking the question right but then
wouldn't the planks con wouldn't the uh
the UN basic uncertain F relation
prevent any further
compression so to speak in the face
space if we were looking at the black H
so the problem
is that in order to have a resistance
against compression you have to have a
reasonable density of
matter uh and a reasonable amount of
kinetic energy and so forth and uh then
you can't squeeze it because you can
squeeze it Bas space but if you look at
how dense something has to be in order
for it to form a horizon the answer
is if it's heavy enough the density of
it can be
negligible um the kind of forces you're
talking about would prevent
collapse it does have to do with the uh
with the incompressibility of face space
but just think of the incompressibility
of face space providing the spatial
force uh which keeps things from
collapsing and you get into trouble
typically in compressing when pressure
gets too big when density gets too
large how large you have to make the
density to make black hole let's try
toate it you have a given amount of
matter
row
that's mass is equal to 2
mg/
[Music]
R Mass
I'm getting tired um it's getting late
just about finished
uhg isal to
R um c
yeah
okay let's divide this by R
Cub
okay why because I'm interested in M RQ
which is
bity the bigger the black hole more
massive the black hole the smaller the
density of a collection of material
would have to be before it forms a black
hole
why take enough
Mass and you put it in the volume the
density only has to be of order what
does this mean i r is of order is equal
to 2 mg 2 mg^
s so if you have a given amount of mass
in order to make it take a form a black
hole the density only has to be 1 2 mg^
s this is why people are very very
certain that black holes form they were
very certain before uh before there were
astronomical observations you don't have
to make it you had enough
Mass arbitrarily low density arbitrarily
low density let's say it another
way let's take an arbitrarily low
density row row is as small as you like
particles every 60 M or whatever it
is now taking big enough
volume enough of them but big enough
radius of them how much mass let's take
let's take a radius off
R that's the radius R how much mass is
there well row *
R 4 Pi so uh
no 43k
R this is order of magnitude the amount
of mass is there right
so R even for this very low density R
the radius of the ball of mass is M over
row and row is fixed row is just this
very low density to the 1/3
power no matter how small row is if you
make M biggest enough this will be less
than tce
mg why because this increases linearly
with M and this only increases as M 1/3
power so for a fixed but tiny row you
can eventually make M over row to the
1/3 smaller than the Schwarz Shield
radius once it's smaller than the
Schwarz Shield radius it's a
black so so no matter how rarified
material is if you create enough of
it if you take the uh
um vacuum energy certain energy density
what would be the
associated um for radius to create a
black hole that
that's with the known
cosmological radius of the universe is
that what would radius of the Horizon of
the yeah really yeah
yeah so I think we can be pretty sure
that in our universe there cannot be a
black hole of size bigger than 10
billion light years so can we in can we
consider ourselves being inside a black
hole no not inside a black hole but
inside an inside out black hole
it's an inside out black hole and that
yes surrounded by a horizon but the
analog of the inside of the Horizon is
the outside of the uh of the
region we on the inside of this sphere
are as if we are on the outside of the
Horizon and outside the
Horizon Things Fall
toward Things Fall away from
us they don't fall toward us on a big
enough scale
because of the Dark Energy Things Fall
away from us they don't fall toward us
that's the that's the accelerated
expansion of the universe Things Fall
away from us and because they fall away
from us eventually if you go far enough
out you will find them moving faster
than the speed of light relative to you
and that becomes sort of exterior
arising but it's not like being on the
inside of black hole being on the inside
of a black hole you crash into a
singularity eventally being on the
inside of a cosmic Horizon just stay gr
well if if Singularity is the End of
Time how does it ever happen if you do
it oh the end of time is probably wrong
it's the end of time in the sense that
death is the end of
time there proper time the proper time
to the singularity is fine so when have
a fixed r at that point and and that's
at Singularity even though R is zero you
would still have a fixed R which would
put you traveling Theory faster than the
at
singular say it
again when R is zero at the singularity
then you also have a fixed R which would
you can fix R because to fix R you have
to exceed the speed of light right yeah
but so but you would have a fix r at r
at Singularity it would be a fix r
well as I said I mean the physics of
what happens when something hits the
singularity is um obscure
best there's no sense in which it stops
it just I don't know what to say about
it physics doesn't know how to get there
density become so large um pressures
become so large P for become so large
that no matter how much physics you know
it will always go beyond that
no physic temperature will become
infinite pressures will become infinite
densities will become infinite so if you
know and think you understand physics
some
desired density that means that you can
understand what happens give the
singularity to some
shell but it'll always get worse you L
long enough not very long it'll get
worse and you'll always be driven beyond
what we know about
matter
so um is it the problem that we don't
know enough to figure out what happens
at the singularity well I don't think so
I don't think that's the point I think
um
uh nothing survives to find
out it seems to be as long as you stay
outside it's also irrelevant but that's
true because nothing nothing goes on on
the other side
that's right that's right but you could
jump in find out you could jump
in if you're outside the black hole you
stay outside the black hole the
singularities are you jump into the
black hole to try to find out what
happens in The Singularity you're not
going to find out
either
tell it's not only that it's not only
that
eventually let's let's look at let's
look at let's take two atoms for the
singularity here's a
singularity now Adams can send back and
forth messages
messages can simply be the photons that
make up field but uh the fact that this
this Adam is influenced by that atom
well we know atoms influence each other
and so forth but when they get too close
to the singularity this atom over here
cannot send the signal to the other
one why there's not enough time to send
a signal they fall out of causal contact
with each other they can no longer
influence each other and so as you get
closer and closer to the singularity the
atoms of your body fall out of contact
with each
other and you just disintegrate into a
Col ction of uncoupled atoms that have
no connection between them but it's
worse than that the electrons in the
atom fall out of contact out of
communication with the
nucleus and protons and neutrons inside
nucleus fall out of contact with each
other so everything just disintegrates
into completely uncouple
[Music]
um
uh something
bits which don't talk to each other is
that
really
the the approximation that you made on
the Met to make a correspondence to the
regular geometry only work where R is
near the
r yes so by going near the singularity
you're going far from the short Shi
radius at sub level you are so
but I've drawn the picture of what that
uh what that met really does look like
within the Horizon also and that's what
you see okay so there's some other
approximations that that that make it
right on the other side
yeah so that's more like a diagram than
a sity
CL
up Singularity
what but on the other the other side of
sity
yeah uh the metric is just still defined
on the other side of
it it's just not defined on the other
side of it or if it is Define nobody
knows well you you simply go through uh
which is totally Unown but I think I
mean the coordinate exists right there's
a ke that's that's larger than that well
how do you how do you all right so if
you're mathematician you could ask can
you analytically continue the metric ask
that
uh to where to um to what to
R you can just yeah just value on the
side
and and then the other question is let's
can
you
R so we want R to
be where do we want to continue this we
want to continue this
where so what happens if you try to
continue this to R
negative uh this becomes positive
this becomes
negative it
is and is it obv that I mean there's no
M there's no
matter is it obvious
that can't go that
surface
well look you could draw like
[Music]
but we can't find out even if we're
willing to jump into the black hole we
can't find
out you mention one time I don't think
information is lost
that's that's F what's the
argum uh let's let's not get into that
now let beyond my P
rice okay when Alice goes through the
Horizon and she's carrying meter stick
met suddenly become a CL no
[Music]
czy things Happ
Alice here's Shirley Shirley is at one
end of a met stick and Alice is at the
other end here's a met stick here's a
met stick nothing happens to it it just
goes straight through there's nothing
fancy happening at the Horizon no the
mck does not become a clock moreover
Alice's clock does not become a Meck
it's just using stupid
coordinates using stupid coordinates
which you call our but you should have
called something else when it gets
behind the
Horizon just because you call it R
doesn't mean you
measure actually there's no
difference
and there's no difference between a and
because how how do we measure time if
you think about how we measure time
you'll end
up you can use met sticks to help you
measure time meter stick is a meter
stick there's nothing else there's
nothing else that is non mechanical or
physical that that
def nothing nothing dramatic happens to
Alice and as they
abely right and Al is sending a signal
that she have right is she going to see
any anything change as she goes over the
horizon or is it going to do the same
Bob has a reflector right if she's
sending a message she's receiving a
message so Bob has a reflector but the
reflection doesn't
is Bob now we do have to keep track of
the fact that Bob is accelerating away
from uh from but that's
okay Alice is
here sorry what is Alice she's PR
falling in she's still outside yeah she
was she outside outside and she sends a
light
beam oops here she is
right Singularity over here Alice sends
a message and the message comes back yep
Alice sends a message from over here and
the message comes back behind the
Horizon but from here Alice can no
longer send a
message so she can send so she'll know
that something
[Music]
happened she knows she knows
get well but she wouldn't know that
while she's procing The Horizon no
that's right feel that's right so so
what she sees is when she sends a
message the messages take longer and
longer to get
back she send a message from here it
just takes a very very let's forget the
singularity if she sends a message from
here it takes a very very long time for
it to get back and what's more it gets
back very very red shap so as she gets
closer and closer to the The Horizon and
sends out her just usual radio waves
those radio waves have to get the B
which takes a very long time and then
they have to come back which takes the
same time and they have and the moving
mirror has red shifted the photons so
the photons get very very red shifted
and so what Alice would see would be a
very very red shifted version of what
she's
saying but and but she cannot see
an image from here
there so why is the maximum wavelength
size of the black hole from that
analysis it seem we're just stretch no
no we need some qu Mechanics for
that
Maxim how is
[Music]
GRA gravitational
force we do it by gra you're taking too
literally the idea the gravitational
force comes from
gra back and forth that's uh
that or if you like you can think of the
gravitons as being emitted from near the
surface of the black hole you can it's
perfectly okay to imagine that all the
material of the black hole accumulates
since it never gets through the Horizon
it must accumulate at the Horizon it
must keep sinking in closer and closer
asymptotically getting closer and
closer but all of the mass is
concentrated in a little little thin
shell from the point of view of somebody
outside is concentrated in a very thin
shell when your horizon uh if you like
to think of gravitons being jumping back
and forth okay do it but they're jumping
back and forth the surface just above
the
Horizon so from outside just think of
the material as collecting in kind of
sedimentary layers which are forever
falling closer and closer this is a
classical statement which are forever
falling closer and closer and thinner
and thinner sedimentary layers never
quite getting there but their mass is
there the mass is there you can tell the
mass is there because you put a surface
around there and this gravitation field
out and you can always think of it as
the mass being localized just in a very
very thin
layer black holes are not symmetric that
might for might be
rotating or so they would be flattened
out or something that sort extremely
flattened out there's a limit on how
fast they can rotate and how asymmetric
they
get so so basically they can't look a
whole lot
different these things here that's right
rotating black holes don't look a whole
lot and they they couldn't have parts to
them like uh inside have Parts rotating
around each other but for example the a
clap a binary star that's collapsed
and
binary some kind of a binary object that
was that fit inside a black hole the the
the piece would collapse out a
singularity and it would stop that yeah
I you we have a couple of binary things
going around each other inside a black
Hall
okay that's really not very that
different than atom with electron going
around a
proton and so so there so there's no
need for example for graviton to escape
the black hole and tell us that's what's
going on don't need and it's not
[Applause]
[Music]
possible the proceeding program is
copyrighted by Stanford University
please visit us at stanford.edu